Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York (ACUSNY); Records apap003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York (ACUSNY) Records
1938-1992
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York
apap003
22.5 cubic ft.
An early organization representing higher education before the Legislature and the Executive in Albany, as well as the Federal Government in Washington D.C.
Administrative History
The Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York (ACUSNY) was founded in 1906 on the initiative of Commissioner of Education Andrew S. Draper and President Nicholas Murray Butler of Columbia University. The founding meeting of the Association included representatives of the municipal colleges of New York City as well as the private colleges and universities, which then accounted for most of the State's small colleges enrollment. The State teachers colleges joined soon thereafter. For approximately fifty years ACUSNY was virtually the only organization representing higher education before the Legislature and the Executive in Albany, as well as the Federal Government in Washington D.C. ["Introduction to ACUSNY". ACUSNY: Albany (N.Y.), undated].
ACUSNY's present membership includes all four sectors of higher education in the State--the State University of New York (SUNY), the City University of New York (CUNY), independent colleges and universities, and proprietary (for profit) colleges authorized by the Board of Regents to confer degrees. Although other organizations now exist to represent the particular needs of these institutions, most institutions maintain their affiliation to ACUSNY, recognizing their unity of purpose, despite differences in their financing and governing structures [In 1956 ACUSNY's private institutions were organized as the constituency of The Commission for Independent Colleges and Universities (CICU), which until 1972 functioned as an integral part of the Association. Following the incorporation of the Association and the Commission by the Regents of The University of the State of New York in May 1972, the Commission became a separate legal entity for the advocacy of independent institutions. Les W. Ingalls, "ACUSNY, Statement of Purpose", 1976]. Rather than representing higher education on specific legislation and executive decisions, ACUSNY now serves members as an information clearing-house on matters where the State Education Department is involved, on relations with other state agencies concerned with activities affecting higher education and on legislation concerning higher education in the State. Through its executive committee, annual, and special meetings the Association provides a forum where college presidents can meet to discuss their common goals and concerns either among themselves or with the leaders of State government, business, elementary and secondary education, and other communities within the State ["Introduction to ACUSNY"].
Since 1985, Business affairs and properties of ACUSNY are managed by the Board of Trustees, which consists of ten trustees of the Commission Independent Colleges and Universities, seven trustees of the State University, three trustees of the City University, and one trustee of the Association of Proprietary Colleges. At the time of the Annual Meeting, the Board of Trustees designates the President, Vice President and Treasurer, and four other trustees, one each from SUNY, CUNY, the Independent and Propriarity sectors from among its membership to form a smaller working group called the executive committee. The executive committee meets periodically with the executive officer to oversee the on-going business of ACUSNY ["Bylaws, Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York", approved at the Annual Meeting, November 22, 1985, and amended at the Annual Meeting, November 3, 1989]. In addition, the Rensselaerville Seminars, which were begun in 1971, offer an opportunity for chief executive officers to speak freely with each other. The major concern is to foster a common bond between public and independent colleges and universities, as well as to explore those areas of mutual concern where joint effort may produce results beneficial to all of higher education in New York State [L.W.I to Clifton R. Wharton, June 13, 1983].
The Association also sponsors, conducts, and cooperates in various projects for the improvement and advancement of higher education in New York State. Some of the major projects with which the Association has been involved include the organization of the emergency colleges for veterans following World War II, the expansion and improvement of the state's student financial aid programs (scholarships, graduate fellowships, scholar incentive awards and tuition assistance), the improvement of education opportunities for the disadvantaged, and the establishment of state aid for private colleges [Les W. Ingalls. "ACUSNY, Statement of Purpose", 1976].
On July 1, 1992 the position of the Executive Director and the Albany Headquarters of the organization were abolished. The Directorship rotates between the State University of New York (SUNY) Chancellor, the City University of New York (CUNY) Chancellor and the President of the Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities (CICU) [Conversation of Geoffrey Williams with George Sussman, Executive Director of ACUSNY, June 15, 1992. ACUSNY].
Scope and Contents
The records of the Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York (ACUSNY) contain minutes of the Board of Trustees, the executive committee and annual meetings; correspondence both to members and to other individuals and institutions involved with higher education in New York; reports both by ACUSNY committees and other education organizations; newsletters; copies of education legislation; and other records that document the concerns and activities of the Association from 1938-1992, and in particular between 1945-1992. The files contain very little information concerning lobbying in Washington, D.C.
Especially complete is the documentation of the executive committee and the annual meetings, and of the Association's involvement in the State legislative process. While illustrating the social, financial, and political concerns of the higher education community as a whole, these records also illuminate the often quite divergent interests of public versus private institutions, especially with regard to the use of state funds.
There are extensive records illustrating the Association's continual efforts towards improving student financial aid and access to higher education, and ensuring fair treatment of educational institutions under state social benefits, taxation, and labor legislation. However, the records also illustrate how the concerns of the educational community were shaped by the larger political and social environment, for example the need for a state university, 1947-1949; universal military training and college deferment 1952; subversion in education, 1953; the use of state bonds for college and university construction, 1955; inter-institutional cooperation, 1956-1973; the expansion of SUNY, 1965; Bundy Aid to private education, 1965-1978; the New York State Constitutional Convention, 1967; and the anti-war protests during the Vietnam War, l969; the establishment of visiting student programs, 1969-1990; the political resolution of educational problems, 1972; the higher education movement, 1975; discussion about problems and prospects of higher education in the next two decades, 1981; statements of principles concerning relations among the sectors, 1983; the establishment of the Minority Faculty Project, 1988-1990; retirement plan, 1990; and service and volunteer programs, 1988-1992.
Arrangement of the Collection
Organized into 13 topical files series.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group, except one, were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York on August 14, 1989 and June 24, 1992. Dennis Dahl donated one publicated, "The Education of a Teacher" in January 2017.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Universities and colleges -- New York (State) -- Finance.; Universities and colleges -- Law and legislation -- New York (State).; Student aid -- New York (State).; Lobbying -- New York (State).; Minutes.; Correspondence.; Education; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Association of Colleges and Universities of the State of New York.; State University of New York.; College of the City of New York (1926-1961); City University of New York.; Commission for Independent Colleges and Universities.
- Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1944-1991; 1; 6 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains meeting minutes, background information sent to Executive Committee members, reports by ACUSNY's Commission on Non-Tax Supported Colleges and Universities, reports by the State Board of Regents, the State Education Department and the University of the State of New York, ACUSNY statements to the Governor and the Legislature, and addresses to the Association's members by prominent figures in the field of education. The series also includes correspondence with the Governor's Office, the Board of Regents, the Commissioner of Education, the Chancellors of the CUNY and SUNY systems, and university and college presidents. This series illustrates ACUSNY's continuous involvement in such issues as admissions policies, student financial aid, state aid to educational institutions and state labor legislation. It also documents the Association's position on specific issues, for example Universal Military Training and college deferment, 1952; sponsorship in athletics, 1951; subversion in education, 1953; the use of state bonds for college and university construction, 1955; educational institutions inter-institutional cooperation, 1956-1973; library reference and research resources, 1963-1965; Bundy aid to private education, 1965-1978; the Constitutional Convention, 1967; visiting students program, 1969-1970; ACUSNY's involvement in federal legislation, 1968, 1973; tuition assistance, 1980; relations among the sectors, 1983; migration patterns of students, 1985; public information activities, 1988; the teaching profession, 1988; creation of new ACUSNY bylaws, 1991.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Meeting, 1950 June 16 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 1)
  - Meeting, 1950 December 6 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 2)
  - Meeting, 1951 March 15 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 3)
  - Meeting, 1951 May 15 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 4)
  - Meeting, 1951 October 25 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 5)
  - Meeting, 1952 March 11 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 6)
  - Meeting, 1952 May 20 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 7)
  - Meeting, 1952 October 24 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 8)
  - Meeting, 1953 March 10 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 9)
  - Meeting, 1953 May 21 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 10)
  - Meeting, 1953 November 6 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 11)
  - Meeting, 1954 March 11 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 12)
  - Meeting, 1954 September 8 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 13)
  - Meeting, 1954 December 16 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 14)
  - Meeting, 1955 March 10 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 15)
  - Meeting, 1955 May 23 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 16)
  - Meeting, 1955 September 9 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 17)
  - Meeting, 1956 March 2 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 18)
  - Meeting, 1956 May 18 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, Minutes, 1944-1991 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 20)
  - Meeting, 1956 September 28 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 21)
  - Meeting, 1957 January 21 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 22)
  - Meeting, 1957 April 23 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 23)
  - Meeting, 1957 November 15 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 24)
  - Meeting, 1958 February 19 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 25)
  - Meeting, 1958 June 20 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 26)
  - Meeting, 1958 September 26 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 27)
  - Meeting, 1958 October 3 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 28)
  - Meeting, 1959 January 14 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 29)
  - Meeting, 1959 March 5 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 30)
  - Meeting, 1959 September 2 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 31)
  - Meeting, 1959 December 2 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 32)
  - Meeting, 1960 March 9 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 33)
  - Meeting, 1960 September 20 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 34)
  - Meeting, 1960 December 7 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 35)
  - Meeting, 1961 March 2 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 36)
  - Meeting, 1961 September 20 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 37)
  - Meeting, 1962 February 11 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 38)
  - Meeting, 1962 September 11 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 39)
  - Meeting, 1963 January 30 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 40)
  - Meeting, 1963 October 7 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 41)
  - Meeting, 1964 January 29 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 42)
  - Meeting, 1964 September 21 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 43)
  - Meeting, 1965 February 11 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 44)
  - Meeting, 1965 October 19 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 45)
  - Meeting, 1966 March 10 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 46)
  - Meeting, 1966 October 18 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 47)
  - Meeting, 1967 March 16 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 48)
  - Meeting, 1967 April 18 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 49)
  - Meeting, 1967 May 16 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 50)
    (Special meeting, Liaison committee).
  - Meeting, 1967 October 17 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 51)
  - Meeting, 1968 February 6 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 52)
  - Meeting, 1968 March 19 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 53)
  - Meeting, 1968 October 23 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 54)
  - Meeting, 1969 February 26 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 55)
  - Meeting, 1969 October 28 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 56)
  - Meeting, 1970 March 3 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 57)
  - Meeting, 1970 October 20 (Box 1 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 58)
  - Meeting, 1973 August 8; 1973 September 25 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 1)
  - Meeting, 1973 November 29 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 2)
  - Meeting, 1974 March 5 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 3)
  - Meeting, 1974 April 22; 1974 June 19 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 4)
  - Meeting, 1974 December 10 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 5)
  - Meeting, 1975 March 18 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 6)
  - Meeting, 1975 June 18 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 7)
  - Meeting, 1975 October 22 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 8)
  - Meeting, 1975 December 4 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 9)
  - Meeting, 1976 February 10 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 10)
  - Meeting, 1976 April 6 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 11)
  - Meeting, 1976 September 16 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 12)
  - Meeting, 1976 October 20 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 13)
  - Meeting, 1976 November 3 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 14)
  - Meeting, 1977 March 9; 2 folders (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 15-16)
  - Meeting, 1977 September 27 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 17)
  - Meeting, 1977 November 7 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 18)
  - Meeting, 1978 March 8 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 19)
  - Meeting, 1978 June 15 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 20)
  - Meeting, 1978 October 3 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 21)
  - Meeting, 1978 December 11 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 22)
  - Meeting, 1979 February 22 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 23)
  - Meeting, 1979 April 17 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 24)
  - Meeting, 1979 June 12 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 25)
  - Meeting, 1979 October 8; 2 folders (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 26-27)
  - Meeting, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 28)
    Includes consideration of institution eligibility for federal funds.
  - Meeting, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 29)
    (Special Meeting on membership and mission).
  - Meeting, 1980 February 20 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 30)
  - Meeting, 1980 June 5 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 31)
  - Meeting, 1980 October 2 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 32)
  - Meeting, 1981 February 19 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 33)
  - Meeting, 1981 October 1 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 34)
  - Meeting, 1981 November 2 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 35)
  - Meeting, 1982 February 17 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 36)
  - Meeting, 1982 June 8 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 37)
  - Meeting, 1982 July 14 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 38)
  - Meeting, 1982 October 6 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 39)
  - Meeting, 1982 December 1 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 40)
  - Meeting, 1983 January 19 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 41)
  - Meeting, 1983 March 16 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 42)
  - Meeting, 1983 June 14 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 43)
  - Meeting, 1983 September 14 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 44)
  - Meeting, 1983 November 22 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 45)
  - Meeting, 1984 January 18; 1984 March 8 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 46)
  - Meeting, 1984 May 3; 1984 May 15 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 47)
  - Meeting, 1984 July 18 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 48)
  - Meeting, 1985 January 30 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 49)
  - Meeting, 1985 April 29 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 50)
  - Meeting, 1985 May 30 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 51)
  - Meeting, 1985 October 1 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 52)
  - Meeting, 1986 April 21 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 53)
  - Meeting, 1986 August 26 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 54)
  - Meeting, 1986 November 6 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 55)
  - Meeting, 1987 February 9 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 56)
  - Meeting, 1987 March 20 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 57)
  - Meeting, 1988 February 26 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 58)
  - Meeting, 1988 March 2 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 59)
  - Meeting, 1988 June 16 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 60)
  - Meeting, 1988 October 27 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 61)
  - Meeting, 1989 March 2 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 62)
  - Meeting, 1990 March 9 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 63)
  - Meeting, Conference Call, 1990 November 9 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 64)
  - Meeting, 1991 July 31 (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 65)
  - Meeting, 1991 October 30; 2 folders (Box 2 (1-Executive Committee Meeting Minutes), Folder 66-67)
- Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planning Retreat, 1971-1991; 2; 4.66 cubic ft.
  The retreats were begun in 1971 at the suggestion of former SUNY Chancellor Boyer to foster a common bond between public and independent colleges and universities. Subsequent to 1985 the retreats came to be known as President's Retreats. The series contains executive committee resolutions, correspondence, and reports from the Board of Regents, the Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities, the State Education Department, the American Council on Education. The contents focus upon particular issues in education: inter-institutional cooperation, 1971; political resolutions of education problems, 1972; student financial support, 1973; projecting college enrollments, 1974; the economics and politics of higher education management, 1975; what labor, government, and the community expect of higher education, 1976; resources for higher education, 1977; federal regulations, academic integrity, and public accountability, 1978; the state's stake in higher education, 1979; higher education and the New York economy, 1981; the role of the president in shaping the undergraduate curriculum, 1984; elevation of higher education among the state's priorities, 1986; connection of community service and college payment, 1989. The series also includes files on president's retreats.
  - Seminar, 1971 (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 1)
    (Interinstitutional Regional Planning).
  - Seminar, 1972; 3 folders (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 2-4)
    (Political Resolution of Educational Problems).
  - Seminar, 1973; 2 folders (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 5-6)
    (Institutional Preservation and Student Financial Support).
  - Seminar, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 7)
    (Enrollment Strategies and Projections).
  - Seminar, 1975; 2 folders (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 8-9)
    (Basic Assumptions for College and University Management).
  - Seminar, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 10)
    (A Pentalogue on the Future of Higher Education in N.Y. State.
  - Seminar, 1977 (Box 1 (2-Rensselaerville Summer Retreats/President's Planni), Folder 11)
    (Resources for Higher Education).